<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Chitas Idea</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Chitas Idea</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://chitasidea.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Fear of Heaven</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/89_fearofheaven/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/89_fearofheaven/</guid><description>23 Teves 5782 &amp;ldquo;The beginning of wisdom is fear of the Lord&amp;rdquo; (Tehillim 111:10)
Fear of Hashem always comes first. In fact, our Sages made many statements regarding the essential trait of yiras Shamayim (fear of heaven). &amp;ldquo;Eliyahu ben Yosef began his discourse in the following manner: The verse states (Tehillim 25:14): &amp;lsquo;Hashem&amp;rsquo;s secret is with those who fear Him, and His covenant is to make them know.&amp;rsquo; This teaches us that the Holy One, Blessed is He, reveals His secrets only to those who fear Him.</description></item><item><title>Everywhere or Nowhere</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/88_everywhereornowhere/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/88_everywhereornowhere/</guid><description>22 Teves 5782 &amp;ldquo;G‑d spoke to Moses, saying to him, &amp;lsquo;I am G‑d. I appeared to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo; (Shemos 6:2-3)
&amp;ldquo;When it appears to us that something is wrong in the way G‑d runs the world, G‑d wants us to question Him. But at the same time, we must continue to believe absolutely in G‑d’s reality and goodness.
From where can we draw the power to believe in G‑d so thoroughly that we virtually see Him even in the darkest moments of exile?</description></item><item><title>Staff in Hand</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/87_staffinhand/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/87_staffinhand/</guid><description>20 Teves 5782 &amp;ldquo;Moses took the staff of G‑d in his hand.&amp;rdquo; (Shemos 4:20)
The Rebbe explains this verse in Chassidus, &amp;ldquo;Even though Moshe gave Pharaoh the honor due a king and spoke to him respectfully, he made no compromises in his demands concerning the people&amp;rsquo;s spiritual and physical needs. He spoke with &amp;lsquo;the staff of G‑d in his hand,&amp;rsquo; i.e., with authority and determination.&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;They will perish, but You will endure; all of them will wear out like a garment; You will exchange them like a robe, and they will vanish.</description></item><item><title>Souls that Have Lost Their Way</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/86_losttheirway/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/86_losttheirway/</guid><description>19 Teves 5782 &amp;ldquo;For forty years I quarreled with that generation; and I said, &amp;lsquo;They are a people of erring hearts, they do not know My ways.'&amp;rdquo; (Tehillim 95:10)
Hashem created different &amp;ldquo;ways&amp;rdquo; (plural) of divine service. The Rebbe in a Sicha on this Parashah (2nd Night of Pesach, 5719, 5720) explains that, &amp;ldquo;There is a specific mission for which every soul descends to this world. When the yetzer hora wants to hinder a person&amp;rsquo;s Divine service, it won&amp;rsquo;t necessarily tell the person to ignore Divine service entirely, for there are those who will not listen to such enticement.</description></item><item><title>Simple</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/85_simple/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/85_simple/</guid><description>18 Teves 5782 &amp;ldquo;[I am regarded] among the dead who are free, like corpses lying in the grave, of whom You are not yet mindful, who are yet cut off by Your hand.&amp;rdquo; (Tehillim 88:6)
Sometimes we put all our strength, or what we think is all of our strength, into our divine service but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel like we are getting anywhere. In those moments it can feel like Hashem has abandoned us, turned away from our efforts.</description></item><item><title>Blind Trust</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/84_blindtrust/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/84_blindtrust/</guid><description>17 Teves 5782 &amp;ldquo;It came to pass, in the course of those many days, that the king of Egypt died; and the children of Israel groaned because of the bondage&amp;rdquo; (Shemos 2:23)
&amp;ldquo;Until this point, the children of Israel were so deeply sunk in their galut that they could not even sense it. But now, when the first budding of their redemption began to emerge (in Moshe&amp;rsquo;s coming of age), they could begin to feel the depth of their suffering.</description></item><item><title>Throwing out the Baby with the Bath Water</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/83_babybathwater/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/83_babybathwater/</guid><description>16 Teves 5782 &amp;ldquo;There went a man of the house of Levi, and took to wife a daughter of Levi&amp;rdquo; (Shemos 2:1)
The Talmud in Sotah 12a explains, &amp;ldquo;Where did he go? He went in the counsel of his daughter. Moses' father, Amram, was the greatest man of his generation. When he saw that the wicked Pharaoh had decreed, &amp;lsquo;Every son that is born you shall throw into the river,&amp;rsquo; he said: We are laboring for nothing!</description></item><item><title>Time-management</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/82_timemanagement/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/82_timemanagement/</guid><description>15 Teves 5782 &amp;ldquo;When a person causes his divine soul to prevail over the animal soul, and when he wages war against the animal soul&amp;rdquo; (Lessons in Tanya, Likutei Amarim, beginning of Chapter 10)
&amp;ldquo;The Baal Shem Tov teaches, one of the problems we have is not having an organized methodology (time-management) to our Divine service – one must regret (Teshuvah) this, and make a positive resolution.&amp;rdquo; (Keser Shem Tov)</description></item><item><title>Up and Down</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/81_updown/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/81_updown/</guid><description>13 Teves 5782 &amp;ldquo;All these are the twelve tribes of Israel, and this is what their father spoke to them and blessed them; each man, according to his blessing, he blessed them.&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 49:28)
Rashi asks an obvious question, &amp;ldquo;Is it not so that some of them he did not bless, but [in fact] chided?&amp;rdquo; Rashi answers, rather than each blessing being addressed individually, all that was stated previously, whether it be blessing or reproach, was in fact addressed to all the brothers.</description></item><item><title>Oil</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/80_oil/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/80_oil/</guid><description>12 Teves 5782 &amp;ldquo;From Asher will come rich food, and he will yield regal delicacies.&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 49:20)
Rashi brings down a story to explain this verse:
&amp;ldquo;The people of Laodicea once needed oil. So they appointed themselves a Gentile messenger. They said to him, &amp;lsquo;Go and bring us oil worth a million (coins).&amp;rsquo; The messenger went to Jerusalem, where they told him, &amp;lsquo;Go to Tyre.&amp;rsquo; So the messenger went to Tyre, where they told him, &amp;lsquo;Go to Giscala (a town in the territory of Asher).</description></item><item><title>Work</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/79_work/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/79_work/</guid><description>11 Teves 5782 &amp;ldquo;Not so in the case of the science of the nations; thereby, one clothes and defiles his divine soul’s faculties of ChaBaD (intellect) with the impurity of the kelipat nogah contained in those sciences &amp;hellip; unless one employs them as a useful instrument, viz., as a means of earning a more affluent livelihood with which to be able to serve G-d, or unless he knows how to apply them in the service of G-d or to his better understanding of His Torah&amp;rdquo; (Lessons in Tanya, Likutei Amarim, Chapter 8)</description></item><item><title>Wasting Seed</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/78_wastingseed/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/78_wastingseed/</guid><description>10 Teves 5782 [Yaakov told Yosef,] &amp;ldquo;But his younger brother will become greater than he.&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 48:19)
Menashe represents our obligation to protect ourselves from the negative influences of our surroundings. Ephraim represents our obligation to influence our surroundings in a positive way. &amp;ldquo;Since before influencing the world we must ensure that we are protected from its temptations, Joseph named his firstborn Menashe, and wished to give him precedence in receiving Yaakov&amp;rsquo;s blessing, as well.</description></item><item><title>Ashes</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/77_ashes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/77_ashes/</guid><description>9 Teves 5782 &amp;ldquo;Why am I afraid in times of trouble? [Because] the sins I trod upon surround me.&amp;rdquo; (Tehillim 49:6)
The Gemara in Rosh Hashannah 17a states that part of the reward for the righetous in the coming world is that the ashes of the wicked are scattered beneath their feet. Why would the righteous want to see the ashes of the wicked under their feet? Rav Mizrachi explains that part of the reward of the righteous is the constant reminder what would have happened had they not done teshuvah.</description></item><item><title>Fox</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/76_fox/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/76_fox/</guid><description>8 Teves 5782 &amp;ldquo;And he said, &amp;ldquo;Swear to me. &amp;quot; So he swore to him, and Israel prostrated himself on the head of the bed.&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 47:31)
Jacob (Israel) bowed to Joseph. Rashi brings an explanation from Talmud Megillah for this. &amp;ldquo;[Although the lion is king] when it is the time of the fox, bow down to him.&amp;rdquo; Although Jacob was in a position of superiority over his son Joseph, he nonetheless recognized when it was Joseph&amp;rsquo;s time to lead and gave him the appropriate respect.</description></item><item><title>Illogical</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/75_illogical/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/75_illogical/</guid><description>6 Teves 5782 &amp;ldquo;The land of Egypt is [open] before you; in the best of the land settle your father and your brothers. Let them dwell in the land of Goshen, and if you know that there are capable men among them, make them livestock officers over what is mine.&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 46:6)
On the face of it, Pharaoh&amp;rsquo;s giving the prime land of Egypt, Goshen, to strangers was illogical. Logic would dictate that such an extraordinary grant would require long preparations, getting to know each other, negotiations, but here in the Parashah we find that Pharaoh gave it just like that.</description></item><item><title>One</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/74_one/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/74_one/</guid><description>5 Teves 5782 &amp;ldquo;All the souls coming to Egypt with Jacob, those descended from him, excluding the wives of Jacob&amp;rsquo;s sons, all the souls were sixty six.&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 46:26)
Rashi comments on this verse, &amp;ldquo;Esau had six souls [in his family], and the text calls them נַפְשׁוֹת בֵּיתוֹ, &amp;lsquo;the souls of his household&amp;rsquo; (Bereishis 36:6) in the plural, because they worshiped many gods [in his family, each his or her own deity].</description></item><item><title>Try Me</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/73_tryme/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/73_tryme/</guid><description>4 Teves 5782 &amp;ldquo;And Israel said, &amp;lsquo;Enough! My son Joseph is still alive. I will go and see him before I die.'&amp;rdquo;
We all have those moments in our lives when we say &amp;ldquo;Enough! Enough sadness, suffering and self-pity, it&amp;rsquo;s time to act now. It&amp;rsquo;s time to rebel against the spirit of indifference. Life is so beautiful. Hashem&amp;rsquo;s Torah is so beautiful. I want to live by it!&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;Through the knowledge and comprehension of Torah by the soul of a person who studies it well, with the concentration of his intellect, to the point where the Torah is grasped by his mind and is joined with him so that they become one, [the Torah thereby] becomes food for the soul.</description></item><item><title>Embrace</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/72_embrace/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/72_embrace/</guid><description>3 Teves 5782 &amp;ldquo;They told [Jacob] all the words of Joseph &amp;hellip; and when he saw the wagons which Joseph had sent to carry him, the spirit of Jacob their father was revived&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 45:27)
Jacob at first did not believe the brothers when they told him Joseph was still alive. When, however, he saw the &amp;ldquo;wagons&amp;rdquo; (agalot) that Joseph had sent, he knew they really were from Joseph, because they hinted at the last topic Joseph and he had studied together, the laws of the &amp;ldquo;eglah arufah.</description></item><item><title>Water</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/71_water/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/71_water/</guid><description>2 Teves 5782 &amp;ldquo;Therefore has the Torah been compared to water, for just as water descends from a higher level to a lower level, so has Torah descended from its place of glory&amp;rdquo; (Lessons in Tanya, Likutei Amarim, middle of Chapter 4)
The water that descends to a lower level is still the same water as at the source. Unlike light, which is a mere ray of its origin, water retains its essential nature.</description></item><item><title>Battlemode</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/70_battlemode/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/70_battlemode/</guid><description>1 Teves 5782 &amp;ldquo;In all of these [Mitzvot, Tanakh, Aggadot, and Midrashim] did G-d &amp;lsquo;compress&amp;rsquo; His will and wisdom in order that every neshamah or ruach and nefesh, in the human body, will be able to grasp them with its intellect and [in order] that it fulfill them, as far as they can be fulfilled, in action, speech, and thought, thereby clothing itself with all its ten faculties in these three garments.</description></item><item><title>Passover</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/69_passover/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/69_passover/</guid><description>29 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;He said, &amp;lsquo;Peace to you; fear not. Your G-d and the G-d of your father gave you a treasure in your sacks&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 43:23)
G-d also gave us a treasure in our sacks, his holy Torah. Although small in size, it contains all the world&amp;rsquo;s knowledge and answers to all questions that we may face. The reason why we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be afraid is not because we trust in worldly authorities - politicians, doctors, scientists - but because we can rely upon the words of our Torah and the Sages who study it.</description></item><item><title>Miracle in Nature</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/68_miracleinnature/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/68_miracleinnature/</guid><description>28 Kislev 5782 [After preparing a gift to send to Joseph, Jacob prayed,] &amp;ldquo;May G‑d Almighty grant that the man be merciful to you.&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 43:14)
&amp;ldquo;Conventional wisdom has it that prayer is necessary only in desperate situations. Thus, Jacob’s sons assumed that since Joseph was detaining their brother because he suspected them of being thieves or spies, it would be enough to pacify him with a gift. From Jacob’s words to his children, however, we learn that even when a favorable outcome seems perfectly natural, we should never assume that we can reach it without Divine assistance.</description></item><item><title>Selfless, Visionary, Trusting</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/67_selflessvisionarytrusting/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/67_selflessvisionarytrusting/</guid><description>27 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;Just as the ten supernal sefirot are divided into two general categories, so, too, with the human soul [and its ten faculties]&amp;rdquo; (Lessons in Tanya, Likutei Amarim, beginning of Chapter 3)
A G-dly soul has three recognizable characteristics: It is selfless, visionary, and trusting. An animal soul also has three recognizable characteristics: It is selfish, constrained, and fearful. If we listen to our G-dly soul we will be selfless, visionary and optimistic/trusting in G-d.</description></item><item><title>Forgetting → Fruitful</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/66_forgettingfruitful/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/66_forgettingfruitful/</guid><description>26 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;Joseph named his firstborn Manasseh &amp;hellip; he named his second son Ephraim.&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 41:51-52)
&amp;ldquo;Joseph named his firstborn Manasseh (meaning &amp;lsquo;[Exile] causes one to forget&amp;rsquo;) in order not to forget his family and heritage. Joseph named his second son Ephraim (&amp;lsquo;he will be fruitful&amp;rsquo;) in order to emphasize that our purpose in the world is to influence it positively&amp;rdquo; (Lubavitcher Rebbe). Exile forces us to unite two seemingly contradictory approaches.</description></item><item><title>Dreams</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/65_dreams/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/65_dreams/</guid><description>25 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;Pharaoh said to Joseph, &amp;lsquo;I had a dream, but there is no one who can interpret it.'&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 41:15)
&amp;ldquo;The dreams of Joseph and Pharaoh led to the Jewish people’s exile in Egypt. Exile was caused by dreams because exile itself is like a dream. In dreams, conflicting and contradictory situations can coexist. Similarly, our behavior in exile seems hypocritical: selflessness and selfishness coexist almost simultaneously.
Living this spiritually inconsistent life is potentially frustrating.</description></item><item><title>Wicked in your Own Eyes</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/64_wickedinowneyes/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/64_wickedinowneyes/</guid><description>24 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;It came to pass at the end of two years&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 41:1)
&amp;ldquo;Every affliction to befall man has a set time to end, as it is written, &amp;lsquo;An end He set to darkness, and every limit He investigates&amp;rsquo; (Job 28:3). This is said regarding Joseph, who had been ten years in prison [when he asked the chief butler to intercede for him], but G‑d investigated and saw that it was necessary for him to be imprisoned for another two years &amp;hellip; &amp;lsquo;In every sorrow there is profit&amp;rsquo; (Proverbs 14:23).</description></item><item><title>Witholding Food</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/63_withholdingfood/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/63_withholdingfood/</guid><description>22 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;It is well known how bitter is the punishment of he who &amp;lsquo;withholds food,&amp;rsquo; i.e., who withholds Torah knowledge from he who seeks it.&amp;rdquo; (Lessons in Tanya, Likutei Amarim, middle of Compiler&amp;rsquo;s Foreword)
It is not allowed to withhold Torah from one who needs it. In our generation all Jews are in need of spiritual sustenance, especially from the elucidated teachings of Chassidus as laid out in the Tanya.</description></item><item><title>Beauty</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/62_beauty/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/62_beauty/</guid><description>21 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;Joseph was beautiful in form and complexion.&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 39:6)
Joseph&amp;rsquo;s physical beauty was a reflection of his inner, spiritual beauty. Our goal too is to perfect ourselves spiritually, attaining a beautiful form and complexion. This however, doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that we should make our own &amp;ldquo;beauty&amp;rdquo; our sole focus, nor that we should keep it all to ourselves. We should not wait until we achieve spiritual perfection before reaching out to others.</description></item><item><title>Imperfection</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/61_imperfection/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/61_imperfection/</guid><description>20 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;All that has remained from the abundance of material is this small number of writings, which have been collected one by one from the copies spread among the disciples.&amp;rdquo; (Lessons in Tanya, Likutei Amarim, Approbations)
The unadulerated words of Tanya were just too pure for this world. The forces of good and evil must always be balanced in this world until Moshiach comes in order for there to be free choice.</description></item><item><title>Living Water</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/60_livingwater/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/60_livingwater/</guid><description>19 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;The pit was empty of water.&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 37:24)
&amp;ldquo;Allegorically, the pit represents the human mind and water represents the Torah. This incident thus tells us that the surest way to keep our mind free of &amp;lsquo;snakes and scorpions&amp;rsquo; – negative and destructive notions – is to ensure that it is always full of Torah-related content, for &amp;lsquo;G‑d’s Torah is wholesome, restoring the soul.'&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;He [the Alter Rebbe] sat at the seat of wisdom with our lord, master, and teacher, the world gaon [the Maggid of Mezritch] and he drew water from the well of living waters.</description></item><item><title>Rebuke</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/59_rebuke/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/59_rebuke/</guid><description>18 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;Reuben heard it, and he saved him from their hands&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 37:21)
Vayikra Rabbah states, &amp;ldquo;Had Reuben known that the Torah would write of him, &amp;lsquo;Reuben heard it, and he saved him from their hands,&amp;rsquo; he would have loaded Joseph on his shoulders and carried him back to his father.&amp;rdquo; Had he known the reward in stow for him, he would not have delayed one second in carrying out this mitzvah.</description></item><item><title>Gathering</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/58_gathering/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/58_gathering/</guid><description>17 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;Joseph dreamed a dream, and told it to his brothers &amp;hellip; &amp;lsquo;Behold, we were binding sheaves in the field, and behold, my sheaf arose and also stood upright; and behold, your sheaves stood all around, and bowed down to my sheaf.'&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 37:5-7)
&amp;ldquo;We live in a disjointed and fragmented world. Its countless components each seem to be going their own way, each creation seeking only its own preservation and advancement.</description></item><item><title>Forgetfulness</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/57_forgetfulness/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/57_forgetfulness/</guid><description>15 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;Since David seized upon [and praised] the hinderpart [of the Torah], he was punished with forgetfulness, which derives from an attitude of externality.&amp;rdquo; (Lessons in Tanya, Kuntres Acharon, end of Essay 6)
A person does not forget things that are truly internalized within him but only things which remain external to him. A person does not forget for example where large sums of money are hidden, when he plans to go on vacation, or what agreements were made in an important business meeting.</description></item><item><title>Exactness</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/56_exactness/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/56_exactness/</guid><description>14 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;So, too, through the use of valid tefillin, there is revealed the supernal intellect of z&amp;rsquo;eyr anpin and nukva, i.e., za and malchut of Atzilut, the source of life for all the worlds. Yet, through [the omission of] one required detail they are invalidated, and the intellect departs.&amp;rdquo; (Lessons in Tanya, Kuntres Acharon, beginning of Essay 6)
When we do a mitzvah with all its exact details &amp;ldquo;all the worlds ascend and receive their life-force and spiritual sustenance&amp;rdquo; from it.</description></item><item><title>Sitra Achra</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/55_sitraachra/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/55_sitraachra/</guid><description>13 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;Even one who crinkles his hair, and the like, receives his life-force at that moment from the spiritual chambers of the kelipot, as is explained in the Zohar.&amp;rdquo; (Lessons in Tanya, Kuntres Acharon, Essay 5)
Even a man who spends time in front of the mirror, manicuring his hair and beard, transgresses the strict will of Hashem. Because of this his life-force in that moment is not drawn from holiness, but from the &amp;ldquo;hinderpart of the ten sefirot of holiness&amp;rdquo; that is the nurture of Kelipot.</description></item><item><title>Almost Done</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/54_almostdone/</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/54_almostdone/</guid><description>12 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;[Jacob] prostrated himself seven times as he approached his brother.&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 33:3)
The Midrash says that, &amp;ldquo;When Mordechai refused to bow to Haman, they said to him: &amp;lsquo;You’re going to get us all killed! How dare you go against the decree of the king?&amp;rsquo; Said Mordechai: &amp;lsquo;I am a Jew.&amp;rsquo; Said they to him: &amp;lsquo;Did not [our] forefathers bow to his forefather?&amp;rsquo; Replied Mordechai: &amp;lsquo;I am a descendant of Benjamin, who was in his mother’s womb at that time.</description></item><item><title>Mission</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/53_mission/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/53_mission/</guid><description>11 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;Jacob remained alone&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 32:25)
The Talmud in Chullin 91a states that &amp;ldquo;He remained for the sake of some small jars he had left behind. Hence it is learned that to the righteous, their money is dearer than their body.&amp;rdquo; How are we to understand this? The Chassidic masters explain that, &amp;ldquo;This is because the righteous know that their material possessions contain &amp;lsquo;sparks of holiness&amp;rsquo; which are redeemed and elevated when the object or resource they inhabit is utilized to fulfill the divine will.</description></item><item><title>Kindness</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/52_kindness/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/52_kindness/</guid><description>10 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;I am unworthy of all the mercies and of all the truth which You have shown Your servant&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 32:11)
&amp;ldquo;The meaning of this is that every kindness bestowed by G-d upon a person should cause him to be exceedingly humble. For a divine kindness is an expression of &amp;lsquo;His right hand embraces me&amp;rsquo; - G-d is literally bringing the person closer to Himself. And the closer a person is to G‑d, the greater the humility this should evoke in him, for since &amp;lsquo;all before Him is as naught,&amp;rsquo; the more &amp;lsquo;before Him&amp;rsquo; a person is, the more &amp;lsquo;as naught&amp;rsquo; does he perceive himself to be.</description></item><item><title>Nuisances</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/51_nuisances/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/51_nuisances/</guid><description>8 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;It was told to Laban &amp;hellip; that Jacob had fled &amp;hellip; He pursued after him a seven days' journey, and overtook him on the mountain of Gilead&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 31:22-23)
The Tzemach Tzedek explains in Ohr HaTorah, &amp;ldquo;Jacob had left behind holy letters which he had not yet extracted from Laban. This is why Laban pursued him — to give him the letters which remained with him. An entire chapter was added to the Torah by these letters.</description></item><item><title>Wealth</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/50_wealth/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/50_wealth/</guid><description>7 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;The drop drawn from the vessel of the supreme wisdom, like the drop that derives from the father’s brain, has the power to procreate and bring about existence ex nihilo.&amp;rdquo; (Lessons in Tanya, Kuntres Acharon, middle of Essay 4)
Emotions and intellect are inherently limited. They cannot descend into the world except in a concealed manner. In contrast, the material derives from a complete source containing the full essence of its Creator.</description></item><item><title>Joseph's Flame</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/49_josephsflame/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/49_josephsflame/</guid><description>6 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;It came to pass, when Rachel had given birth to Joseph, that Jacob said to Laban: &amp;lsquo;Send me away, that I may go to my own place, and to my country&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 30:25)
&amp;ldquo;As soon as Esau&amp;rsquo;s nemesis was born, Jacob no longer feared to return to the Holy Land. As it is written (Obadiah 1:18): &amp;lsquo;The House of Jacob shall be fire, the House of Joseph shall be flame, and the House of Esau — straw&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo; (Rashi).</description></item><item><title>Honor</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/48_honor/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/48_honor/</guid><description>5 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;And it came to pass in the morning, and behold she was Leah!&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 29:25)
Jacob, aware of Laban&amp;rsquo;s trickery, gave over identifying signals to Rachel before the wedding. But when Leah was being led into the bridal chamber, Rachel thought, &amp;ldquo;My sister will now be disgraced,&amp;rdquo; and she entrusted her with the signals. (Rashi)
From here we see how precious the honor of our fellow must be to us.</description></item><item><title>Lightfoot</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/47_lightfoot/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/47_lightfoot/</guid><description>4 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;Light of foot, Jacob set out for the land of the people who lived to the east.&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 29:1)
&amp;ldquo;Even though Jacob was on his way to enter a spiritually dangerous environment, his joy in fulfilling his Divine mission and trust in G‑d’s protection permeated his entire being, down to his feet. Following Jacob’s example, we can adopt the same joyful and confident attitude when we set out to tackle life&amp;rsquo;s numerous daily, mundane activities, even though they may not seem as spiritual.</description></item><item><title>Established</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/46_established/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/46_established/</guid><description>3 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;He delivered me because He desires me.&amp;rdquo; (Tehillim 18:20)
Sometimes we may think, &amp;ldquo;Who are we to stand before Hashem?&amp;rdquo; What did we do to merit Hashem&amp;rsquo;s desire for us?
We must know that this is in no way based on our own doing, but wholly on the merit of our forefathers. They established an eternal covenant with Hashem. We are only the executors of that will, and as such we attain in some way the status of the great people who came before us.</description></item><item><title>Breath</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/45_breath/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/45_breath/</guid><description>1 Kislev 5782 &amp;ldquo;And may the Lord give you of the dew of the heavens and [of] the fatness of the earth and an abundance of grain and wine.&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 27:28)
Rashi explains why the Divine Name signifying G-d&amp;rsquo;s attribute of Justice is used here. He explains that when Solomon arranged the prayer, he would state, &amp;ldquo;And give to every man [Israelite] according to his ways.&amp;rdquo; About the gentile he would say, &amp;ldquo;You shall hear in heaven, etc.</description></item><item><title>Lishmah</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/44_lishmah/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/44_lishmah/</guid><description>29 Cheshvan 5782 [Yitzchok said to Esau,] &amp;ldquo;Prepare &amp;hellip; so that I may grant you my soul&amp;rsquo;s blessing before I die.&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 27:4)
Only Yitzchok&amp;rsquo;s sense of sight was dimmed, not his intellect. Why then did he wish to grant Esau, whose wives were &amp;ldquo;a vexation of the spirit to Isaac and to Rebecca,&amp;rdquo; the mantle of leadership over what would come to be the Holy Jewish Nation?
Yitzchok recognized Esau&amp;rsquo;s potential.</description></item><item><title>Teshuva</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/43_teshuva/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/43_teshuva/</guid><description>28 Cheshvan 5782 [The king of Philistia and his entourage] said [to Yitzchok], &amp;ldquo;We have seen that the Lord was with you; so we said: Let there now be an oath between us, between ourselves and you, and let us form a covenant with you.&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 26:28)
In the end the Philistines approached Yitzchok to make peace. Like Yitzchok&amp;rsquo;s efforts to dig wells, our most well-intentioned efforts can also sometimes yield unexpected results, actually strengthening the forces that oppose holiness rather than doing good.</description></item><item><title>Strife</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/42_strife/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/42_strife/</guid><description>27 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;The measure of good is more generous [than its opposite]&amp;rdquo; (Kuntres Acharon, Essay 1)
The Alter Rebbe brings this passage from Sotah (11a) to explain how verbalized Torah study, even without awe and love, &amp;ldquo;pierces firmaments.&amp;rdquo; This also contains an important lesson for us. Hashem constructed this world asymmetrically, with the potential of good far outweighing the potential of bad.
&amp;ldquo;And he moved away from there, and he dug another well, and they did not quarrel over it&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 26:22)</description></item><item><title>Routine</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/41_routine/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/41_routine/</guid><description>26 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;And it came to pass, when he had been there for many days, that Abimelech, the king of the Philistines, looked out of the window, and he saw, and behold, Isaac was jesting with Rebecca his wife.&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 26:8)
When Isaac came to Philistia, he too, like his father Abraham, pretended that his wife was his sister. After living there undisturbed for a while, &amp;ldquo;he said [to himself], &amp;lsquo;From now on, I need not worry since they have not violated her until now,&amp;rsquo; and he did not take precautions to beware.</description></item><item><title>Circulation</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/40_circulation/</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/40_circulation/</guid><description>25 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;In the writings of Rabbi Yitzchak Luria, of blessed memory, this [dual direction] is referred to as or yashar (&amp;lsquo;direct light&amp;rsquo;) and or chozer (&amp;lsquo;reflected light&amp;rsquo;), i.e., light reflected upward from the lower level back to the upper, as it is also written, &amp;lsquo;And the Chayot were advancing and retreating.'&amp;rdquo; (Lessons in Tanya, Iggeret HaKodesh, Epistle 31)
The life force drawn down to this world from the &amp;ldquo;heart&amp;rdquo;, from the Shechinah, is circulated from the &amp;ldquo;organs&amp;rdquo;, the Jewish souls, back to their original Source through Torah study and prayer.</description></item><item><title>Halacha</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/39_halacha/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/39_halacha/</guid><description>23 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;And to the sons of Abraham&amp;rsquo;s concubines, Abraham gave gifts&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 25:6)
Rashi explains that Abraham gave them &amp;ldquo;all that was given to him because of Sarah and the other gifts that were given to him &amp;hellip; for he did not wish to benefit from them.&amp;rdquo; In Kitzur Shulchan Oruch Chapter 29 &amp;ldquo;Moral and Ethical Rules Which a Person Should Adopt&amp;rdquo; it says, &amp;ldquo;It is the practice of pious people, not to accept gifts, but to trust that Hashem, will take care of their needs.</description></item><item><title>Candle</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/38_candle/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/38_candle/</guid><description>22 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;And Isaac brought her to the tent of Sarah his mother&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 24:67)
Rashi explains, &amp;ldquo;He brought her to the tent, and behold, she was Sarah his mother; i.e., she became the likeness of Sarah his mother, for as long as Sarah was alive, a candle burned from one Sabbath eve to the next.&amp;rdquo; The candle burning from one Shabbos to the next &amp;ldquo;demonstrates the unique ability of Jewish women and girls – who are all &amp;lsquo;daughters&amp;rsquo; of Sarah and Rebecca – to influence the spiritual character of the home, illuminating it with the holiness of the Shabbos throughout the ensuing mundane week.</description></item><item><title>All In</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/37_allin/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/37_allin/</guid><description>21 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;Sarah, my master’s wife, bore a son to my master in her old age; and to him he has given all that he possesses&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 24:36)
&amp;ldquo;As the first Jewish marriage described by the Torah, the union of Isaac and Rebecca is the prototype of all subsequent Jewish marriages, both in the literal sense of building a home in Israel and in the broader sense of uniting the physical world with its cosmic soul, thereby fulfilling the divine purpose in creation of making the world a dwelling place for G‑d.</description></item><item><title>Giving</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/36_giving/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/36_giving/</guid><description>20 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;The maiden to whom I will say, &amp;lsquo;Lower your pitcher and I will drink,&amp;rsquo; and she will say, &amp;lsquo;Drink, and I will also water your camels,&amp;rsquo; her have You designated for Your servant, for Isaac&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 24:14)
&amp;ldquo;Since G‑d lacks nothing, generosity is the primary way in which He relates to the world. For the same reason, generosity is the natural hallmark of people who feel closely connected to G‑d &amp;hellip; When Rebecca went beyond fulfilling Eliezer’s specific request by offering to also water his camels, he understood that she was a G‑dly person and thus a fitting match for the son of Abraham.</description></item><item><title>Women in our Life</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/35_womeninourlife/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/35_womeninourlife/</guid><description>19 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;And Abraham was old, advanced in days, and the Lord had blessed Abraham with everything.&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 24:1)
&amp;ldquo;[The word] בַּכֹּל is numerically equal to בֵּן [son]. Since he had a son, he had to find him a wife&amp;rdquo; (Rashi). The self-evidence with which Rashi draws a connection between having a son and finding him a wife reflects the indispensability of Jewish marriage. Without his partner, a person is incomplete, helplessly exposed to the changing tides of his fate.</description></item><item><title>Generations</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/34_generations/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/34_generations/</guid><description>18 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;I am a stranger and a resident amongst you&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 23:4)
&amp;ldquo;The Jew is a &amp;lsquo;resident&amp;rsquo; in the world, for the Torah instructs him not to escape the physical reality but to inhabit it and elevate it &amp;hellip; At the same time, the Jew feels himself a &amp;lsquo;stranger&amp;rsquo; in the material world &amp;hellip; Indeed, it is only because the Jew feels himself a stranger in the world that he can avoid being wholly consumed and overwhelmed by it.</description></item><item><title>Orchard</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/33_orchard/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/33_orchard/</guid><description>16 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;[The tzadik&amp;rsquo;s ascent] effects a union, between the spiritually feminine sefirah of malchut and the spiritually masculine levels of Divine efflux that transcend it, by means of the elevation of mayin nukvin constituted by all of [the tzaddik’s] actions, his Torah, and the Divine service in which he engaged all the days of his life.&amp;rdquo; (Lessons in Tanya, Iggeret HaKodesh, end of Epistle 27)
This is so because &amp;ldquo;all of man’s lifelong labors and attainments are revealed from their former state of concealment and shine forth at the time of his passing.</description></item><item><title>Advocates</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/32_advocates/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/32_advocates/</guid><description>15 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;Fear not, for God has heard the lad&amp;rsquo;s voice in the place where he is.&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 21:17)
On this verse, Rashi explains that Hashem judges a man &amp;ldquo;according to the deeds that he does now, and not according to what he is destined to do.&amp;rdquo; Even though Ishmael was destined to become a wild man, &amp;ldquo;his hand will be upon all, and everyone&amp;rsquo;s hand upon him,&amp;rdquo; and his descendants were destined to kill the Jews with thirst, Hashem brought up a well for him, because of the righteousness he was currently conducting himself with.</description></item><item><title>Charging Station</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/31_chargingstation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/31_chargingstation/</guid><description>14 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;And when I pondered to understand this, it was unjust in my eyes; until I came to the sanctuaries of God, and perceived their end.&amp;rdquo; (Tehillim 73:16-17)
Sometimes a physical place can have a very profound impact on our spiritual lives. Every person has at least one &amp;ldquo;spiritual charging station,&amp;rdquo; which he can always go to and reconnect to Hashem from. From there he can understand that all of Hashem&amp;rsquo;s ways are just and that it is our mission to go along with them.</description></item><item><title>Tarried</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/30_tarried/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/30_tarried/</guid><description>13 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;&amp;lsquo;This day—to do them,&amp;rsquo; As the Gemara states, &amp;lsquo;Today is the time to do them; tomorrow is the time to receive their reward.&amp;rsquo; Man’s primary task in this world is the actual fulfillment of the commandments while the receipt of rewards or anything akin to rewards belongs to &amp;lsquo;tomorrow,&amp;rsquo; to the World to Come.&amp;rdquo; (Lessons in Tanya, Iggeret HaKodesh, middle of Epistle 27)
Our mission in this world is action.</description></item><item><title>Immortal</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/29_immortal/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/29_immortal/</guid><description>12 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;For I have known him because he commands his sons and his household after him, that they should keep the way of the Lord to perform righteousness and justice, in order that the Lord bring upon Abraham that which He spoke concerning him.&amp;rdquo;&amp;quot; (Bereishis 18:19)
Rashi expounds &amp;ldquo;It does not say &amp;ldquo;upon the house of Abraham&amp;rdquo; but &amp;ldquo;upon Abraham.&amp;rdquo; We learn from this that whoever raises a righteous son is considered as though he does not die.</description></item><item><title>Milk and Meat</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/28_milkmeat/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/28_milkmeat/</guid><description>11 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;And he took cream and milk and the calf that he had prepared, and he placed [them] before them&amp;rdquo; (Bereishis 18:8)
This verse seemingly implies that Avraham served his guests milk and meat together. This would contradict the concept that all the Avot observed the entire Torah, written, oral, and rabbinic. On further inspection though, the commentaries explain, &amp;ldquo;seeing that Avraham is reported as first having served milky dishes, and the meat subsequently, it is reasonable to assume that &amp;hellip; the interval would have sufficed not to violate the laws of mixing milk and meat.</description></item><item><title>Reason</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/27_reason/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/27_reason/</guid><description>9 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;And he split them in the middle&amp;rdquo; (Bereishit 15:10)
&amp;ldquo;Our sages explain the symbolism in the animals which G‑d told Abraham to take. On one level, they correspond with the various offerings brought by the Jewish people in the Holy Temple. On another level, they represent the galut of Israel in its various incarnations — the powers to which the Jewish people will be subject in the course of their history (Egypt, Babylon, Persia, Greece, Rome, etc.</description></item><item><title>Chitzonim</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/26_chitzonim/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/26_chitzonim/</guid><description>8 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;For this reason, study chiefly involves deliberation and argumentation on the laws of issur and hetter, impurity and purity, in order to disencumber the permitted and the pure from the forbidden and the impure by means of deliberation and argumentation on the law—with wisdom, understanding, and knowledge&amp;rdquo; (Lessons in Tanya, Iggeret HaKodesh, middle of Epistle 26)
At present the Shechinah vests itself in the material realm and &amp;ldquo;grants life-force to the chitzonim that belong in the realm of kelipat nogah.</description></item><item><title>Thought, Speech, Deed</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/25_thoughtspeechdeed/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/25_thoughtspeechdeed/</guid><description>7 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;Thus, it is taught explicitly in Sefer Hakavanot — that Scripture, Mishnah, Talmud, and Kabbalah are all in Atzilut, except that Scripture vests itself as far [&amp;ldquo;down&amp;rdquo;] as Asiyah, and Mishnah [vests itself only] as far [&amp;ldquo;down&amp;rdquo;] as Yetzirah, and Talmud is vested as far [&amp;ldquo;down&amp;rdquo;] as Beriah.&amp;rdquo; (Lessons in Tanya, Iggeret HaKodesh, middle of Epistle 26)
Asiyah corresponds to soul-garment of deed, Yetzirah corresponds to the soul-garment of speech, and Beriah corresponds to the soul-garment of thought.</description></item><item><title>Muttar</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/24_muttar/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/24_muttar/</guid><description>6 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;For Sin makes itself appealing to him, until his iniquity be found and he is hated.&amp;rdquo; (Tehillim 36:3)
Sin can make itself appealing even to a person with the best possible intentions. To the undiscerning and well-meaning eye, something dangerous can seem like an object waiting to be uplifted to holiness. By such deception, a person with only good intentions can venture onto the other side, subjugating his actions to the sitra achara and being drawn into it against his will.</description></item><item><title>Regression</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/23_regression/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/23_regression/</guid><description>5 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;And it came to pass when Abram came to Egypt&amp;rdquo; (Bereishit 12:14)
Instead of being allowed to pursue his monotheistic revival in G‑d&amp;rsquo;s Promised Land, Abraham was thrust into the world’s most prominent bastion of paganism. How ironic that the ambitious monotheist was suddenly reduced to seeking the mercy of a cultural environment that mocked his every ideal. Yet, in a miraculous reversal of fortune, Abraham shortly thereafter returned to the Land of Israel with greater wealth and with a greater reputation.</description></item><item><title>Rashbi</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/22_rashbi/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/22_rashbi/</guid><description>4 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;Abram took with him his wife, Sarai &amp;hellip; and the souls which they had made in Charan&amp;rdquo; (Bereishit 12:5) - Rambam: &amp;ldquo;No sooner was this mighty one weaned — and he was but a child — than his mind began to seek and wonder: How do the heavenly bodies circle without a moving force? Who turns them? They cannot move themselves! Immersed amongst the foolish idol-worshippers of Ur Casdim, he had no one to teach him anything: his father, mother and countrymen, and he amongst them, all worshipped idols.</description></item><item><title>Lashon Hara</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/21_lashonhara/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/21_lashonhara/</guid><description>2 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;Who may abide in Your tent, O Lord? &amp;hellip; He who has no slander on his tongue, who has done his fellowman no evil&amp;rdquo; (Tehillim 15:1-3)
Lashon Hara is one of the most serious sins in the Torah. So much so that it can completely separate us from Hashem and prevent us from welcoming the Shechinah in the coming world. The Chofetz Chaim enumerates 17 positive and negative commandments in the Torah that are being violated each time a Jew speaks Lashon Hara.</description></item><item><title>Sparks</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/20_sparks/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/20_sparks/</guid><description>1 Cheshvan 5782 &amp;ldquo;[G-d said,] &amp;ldquo;Never again will there be a flood to destroy the earth.&amp;rdquo;&amp;rdquo; (Bereishit 9:11)
&amp;ldquo;When the Torah says that G‑d &amp;ldquo;destroyed the earth,&amp;rdquo; it means that He destroyed &amp;ldquo;earthiness&amp;rdquo; – i.e., the mistaken belief that the world exists independent of G‑d. The Flood completely submerged the world in Divine awareness, and thus purified it from its moral degeneration and made it permanently receptive to Divine consciousness.&amp;rdquo; (Daily Wisdom) This omnipresent receptiveness to Divine consciousness is closely related to the Chassidic concept of Birurim, elements of spiritual refinement and purification latent within all material things waiting to be uplifted to holiness by a Jew.</description></item><item><title>Outloud</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/19_outloud/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/19_outloud/</guid><description>30 Tishrei 5782 &amp;ldquo;And the Lord smelled the pleasant aroma&amp;rdquo; (Bereishit 8:21)
The deep reasons behind why Hashem in all His power and glory cares about our lowly offerings, either physical or in prayer, is beyond us. We just need to know that they have a tremendous effect on High. So too in this Parashah, the covenant to never bring about such devastation on the earth again was brought about through a simple offering from a pure heart.</description></item><item><title>Power of Prayer</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/18_powerofprayer/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/18_powerofprayer/</guid><description>29 Tishrei 5782 &amp;ldquo;O Lord, place a guard for my mouth, keep watch over the door of my lips.&amp;rdquo; (Tehillim 141:3)
Not only does this verse in Psalms speak to the importance of guarding your own words, it also teaches an important lesson about prayer. As Rashi comments, &amp;ldquo;When I pray before You, I should speak poetically, that it should be acceptable.&amp;rdquo; It is crucial for our own life and the life force of the world to draw down blessings through the channels of prayer.</description></item><item><title>Wellsprings</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/17_wellsprings/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/17_wellsprings/</guid><description>28 Tishrei 5782 &amp;ldquo;In the six-hundredth year of Noah’s life &amp;hellip; all the fountains of the great deep broke open, and the windows of heaven were opened&amp;rdquo; (Bereishit 7:11)
&amp;ldquo;[This hints that] in the sixth century of the sixth millennium [from creation — 1740–1840 in the secular calendar], the gates of supernal wisdom will be opened, as will the springs of earthly wisdom, preparing the world to be elevated in the seventh millennium.</description></item><item><title>Pure Motives</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/16_puremotives/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/16_puremotives/</guid><description>27 Tishrei 5782 &amp;ldquo;G‑d said to Noah &amp;hellip; &amp;ldquo;Make yourself an ark&amp;rdquo;&amp;rdquo; (Bereishit 6:13–14)
&amp;ldquo;When the Flood came, Noah and his family entered the ark—alone. His 120-year campaign yielded not a single baal teshuvah! Perhaps public relations was never Noah’s strong point, but how are we to explain the fact that in all this time he failed to win over a single individual? In order to influence others, one’s motives must be pure; in the words of our sages, &amp;ldquo;Words that come from the heart enter the heart.</description></item><item><title>Disturbance</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/15_disturbance/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/15_disturbance/</guid><description>25 Tishrei 5782 &amp;ldquo;A worshipper who finds that his endeavors to concentrate are being disturbed by someone speaking should consider: &amp;ldquo;Why did G-d bring me here, where this talker is disturbing my prayers? After all, everything is Providential.&amp;rdquo; Indeed it is, explains the Baal Shem Tov: this man’s talk is a spark of the radiance of the Shechinah that has descended and now &amp;ldquo;abides&amp;rdquo; in his mouth in order that the worshipper should exert himself so strenuously that he will be able to ignore the disturbance.</description></item><item><title>Beauty</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/14_beauty/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/14_beauty/</guid><description>24 Tishrei 5782 &amp;ldquo;And Lemech took himself two wives.&amp;rdquo; (Bereishit 4:19)
There are few things as opposed to the Torah as the objectification of female beauty. Right at the beginning of the Torah, in Parashah Bereishit, Hashem condemns the practice of separating beauty from its spiritual root and purpose. By Lemech’s time, society had morally degenerated to the point that men were marrying one woman for her beauty and a second woman for the purpose of procreation.</description></item><item><title>Ecstatic Joy</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/13_ecstaticjoy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/13_ecstaticjoy/</guid><description>21 Tishrei 5782 &amp;ldquo;This is why the hearts of those who seek G-d are ecstatically aroused at the time of prayer and the like.&amp;rdquo; (Lessons in Tanya, Iggeret HaKodesh, middle of Epistle 23)
In this Tanya portion the Alter Rebbe beautifully describes the overwhelming pleasure chassidim feel &amp;ldquo;when their souls delight in the pleasantness of G-d and His light.&amp;rdquo; However, this joy is limited and it only follows an arousal from below through careful adherence to the ways of Hashem, first and foremost in the intellectual faculties.</description></item><item><title>Messudar</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/12_messudar/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/12_messudar/</guid><description>20 Tishrei 5782 &amp;ldquo;I shall walk with the innocence of my heart [even] within my house.&amp;rdquo; (Tehillim 101:2)
Chassidus centers around this concept. We can&amp;rsquo;t be one thing outside the house and another inside. Our fear of G-d must permeate our entire life, into the innermost recesses of our heart and the most private parts of our lives. From here derives also the concept that a chossid must be a &amp;ldquo;messudar.</description></item><item><title>Alone</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/11_alone/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/11_alone/</guid><description>18 Tishrei 5782 &amp;ldquo;And Israel dwelled safely and alone&amp;rdquo; (Devarim 33:28)
Rashi elaborates that &amp;ldquo;every single individual [will dwell safely] - each man under his own vine and his own fig tree.&amp;rdquo; This comes to teach us that when we are truly with Hashem our security is already guaranteed. No further measures are required to protect ourselves. We can live according to our own beliefs. As long as these align with Hashem&amp;rsquo;s, our success is guaranteed.</description></item><item><title>Strength to Strength</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/10_strengthtostrength/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/10_strengthtostrength/</guid><description>17 Tishrei 5782 &amp;ldquo;The days of your old age will be like the days of your youth.&amp;rdquo; (Devarim 33:25)
Apart from the obvious first interpretation, Rashi offers an alternative explanation on this verse, that &amp;ldquo;the days which can be enumerated as your good days, namely, all those days on which you fulfilled the will of the Omnipresent - so will be &amp;ldquo;your flowing,&amp;rdquo; i.e., all the countries [in the world] will make silver and gold flow into the Land of Israel.</description></item><item><title>Alacrity &amp; Consistency</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/09_alacrityconsistency/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/09_alacrityconsistency/</guid><description>14 Tishrei 5782 &amp;ldquo;Whoever does so frequently is praiseworthy, rather than at one time and all at once, even when the total sum is the same. Even then, it is far preferable to give the same amount over a longer period on numerous occasions&amp;rdquo; (Lessons in Tanya, Iggeret HaKodesh, end of Epistle 21)
Alacrity and consistency are the two most important character traits for a Jew to survive in our generation of hyperactivity and distractions.</description></item><item><title>Tevah</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/08_tevah/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/08_tevah/</guid><description>13 Tishrei 5782 &amp;ldquo;Indeed, You showed love for peoples; all his holy ones are in Your hand&amp;rdquo; (Devarim 33:3)
The souls of the righteous are hidden away with G-d. They cling on to Him, they do not turn away from Him. He in turn guards them. It is said that in times of hardship Jews should flee into the תֵבָה. The word תֵבָה has several meanings. It can refer to Noah&amp;rsquo;s Ark, his תֵבָה, into which he fled when the waters of the Great Flood came to cleanse the world of defilement.</description></item><item><title>Land</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/07_land/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/07_land/</guid><description>11 Tishrei 5782 &amp;ldquo;He will &amp;hellip; appease His land [and] His people.&amp;rdquo; (Devarim 32:43)
Rashi elaborates on this verse &amp;ldquo;And what is His land? His people. When His nation is comforted, His land is also comforted. Thus, Scripture says, &amp;ldquo;O Lord, You have appeased Your land&amp;rdquo; (Tehillim 85:2). How have You appeased Your land? [That same verse continues:] “You have returned the captivity of Jacob.&amp;rdquo; The inherent spiritual power in the land is the same spiritual power that lies latent within every Jew.</description></item><item><title>Torah vs. Mitzvos</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/06_torahvsmitzvos/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/06_torahvsmitzvos/</guid><description>9 Tishrei 5782 &amp;ldquo;But to the wicked, G-d said, &amp;ldquo;What does it help you to discuss My laws, and bear My covenant upon your lips?&amp;rdquo; (Tehillim 50:16)
This verse in Tehillim comes to rebuke those who do not practice that which they study, and merely appear to be righteous; they sin and cause others to sin.
&amp;ldquo;And even Torah study itself presupposes the prior performance of the mitzvot — for they are its beginning and on them depends its very existence&amp;rdquo; (Lessons in Tanya, Iggeret HaKodesh middle of Epistle 20)</description></item><item><title>Clarity</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/05_clarity/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/05_clarity/</guid><description>8 Tishrei 5782 &amp;ldquo;And Jeshurun became fat and rebelled; you grew fat, thick and rotund&amp;rdquo; (Devarim 32:15)
Over time our relationship with Hashem can become confused. By praying to Him for our needs we can start seeing Him as obligated to us in some way, chaz ve shalom even as our servant. We can become so involved in our needs, material but even spiritual, that we blind ourselves to the true nature of our relationship with him, that of complete nullification.</description></item><item><title>Tzimtzum</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/04_tzimtzum/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/04_tzimtzum/</guid><description>7 Tishrei 5782 &amp;ldquo;As an eagle awakens its nest, hovering over its fledglings&amp;rdquo; (Devarim 32:11)
Rashi comments on this verse &amp;ldquo;[The eagle] does not impose its [whole] body upon them. Rather, it hovers above them, touching them and yet not quite touching them.&amp;rdquo; Were Hashem to thrust His full might onto us we would simply seize existing.
&amp;ldquo;The original tzimtzum that occurred in the [infinite] Ein Sof-light, a tzimtzum of such intensity that it was able to bring about a void — a “space” — for the existence of worlds&amp;rdquo; (Lessons in Tanya, Iggeret HaKodesh middle of Epistle 20)</description></item><item><title>Catch you when you fall</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/03_catchwhenyoufall/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/03_catchwhenyoufall/</guid><description>6 Tishrei 5782 &amp;ldquo;If he falls, he will not be cast down, for the Lord supports his hand.&amp;rdquo; (Tehillim 37:24)
King David assures us, from his own personal experience, that Hashem is not keen to cast us away to be forsaken. When we put our trust in Hashem, He will protect us from ourselves, even when we set out on the wrong path. He will send us not only one, but multiple warnings and will always open up the door for us to return.</description></item><item><title>Highest/Lowest</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/02_highestlowest/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/02_highestlowest/</guid><description>4 Tishrei 5782 &amp;ldquo;In the evolving and descending chainlike progression called Hishtalshelut, the lowest link remains connected — i.e., retains some qualitative relationship — to the highest link.&amp;rdquo; (Lessons in Tanya, Iggeret HaKodesh Epistle 20)
The last thought in creation actually came first. The entire order of contractions, ilah (&amp;ldquo;causes&amp;rdquo;) and alah (&amp;ldquo;effects&amp;rdquo;), was set up only so that we should be able to build a dwelling place for Hashem in this world, specifically through the mitzvot involving action.</description></item><item><title>Hidden Hidden</title><link>https://chitasidea.com/post/01_hiddenhidden/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chitasidea.com/post/01_hiddenhidden/</guid><description>3 Tishrei 5782 &amp;ldquo;And I will hide My face&amp;rdquo; (Devarim 31:18)
There are times when G‑d hides His face. Then there are times when G‑d hides His face and He also hides the fact that His face is hidden. In this kind of galut, we dwell in darkness thinking it is light. It is a double galut, a concealment within a concealment.
&amp;ldquo;Only G-d Himself has the ability to create a being so corporeal that it is entirely unaware that its existence depends on a Creator; indeed, it is satisfied with the delusion that it is responsible for its own creation.</description></item></channel></rss>